Guide to the El Espectador: weekly Spanish language newspaper, 1937-1960
Department of Special Collections
El Espectador: weekly Spanish language newspaper,
1937-1960
Special Collections M0255
18 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Mrs. Ingnacio L. Lopez, 1975.
Biographical Note
Ignacio Lutero Lopez Collection
March 19, 1908 to July 4, 1973
Born: Guadalajara, Jalisco, Mexico
Education: Pomona public schools
Pomona High School (graduated 1927)
Chaffey College, Ontario, Ca. (1928-29)
Pomona College, Claremont, Ca. (1930-31) A.B.
Univ. of Calif., Berkeley, Ca. (1931-32) M.S.
UCLA, Los Angeles, Ca. (1953-54; 1957-58) pre-doctoral
Sociology; Political Science; Education.
Received Medalla de Honor and a $1000. award to the Latin-American student who made the greatest contribution to UCB in 1932.
Employment
1933-1960 Editor and publisher of El Espectador a weekly bilingual paper
1941-1942 Senior Cultural Officer Foreign Language Division Office of War Information Washington, D.C. - under Alan Cranston prepared press releases and radio news letters for Spanish papers; organized Victory Councils among different ethnic groups.
1942-1943 West Coast Rep. of Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs Washington, D.C. - under Nelson Rockefeller directed greater Mexican-American participation in nation: less high school dropouts and higher educational achievements; better job and business development and civic involvement
1944-1945 Senior Fair Practices Examiner President's Com. on FEP Washington, D. C. - under Harry Kingman head of L. A. office until end of World War II
1951-1953 Asst. to Information Director City of L.A. Housing Authority - under Howard Holzendorff organized relocation of Chavez Ravine; Rose Hills; Aliso Village Annex and Pacoima Projects
1961-1963 Information and Relocation Specialist L.A. Community Redev. Agcy. - under Joe T. Bill public relations and relocation work in Bunker Hill Project; rewrote agency's pamphlets, etc.
1963 Coordinator, Campaign to Re - Elect Norris Poulson LA Mayor - primaries organizer for Poulson's third term
1964-65 Director, Public Relations Tetela Community Hospital Lomas de Tetela, Cuernavaca Morelia, Mexico -under Dr. Joe Revituso promotion from proposed hospital to completion of site
1964 Director, Mex.-Am. Campaign to Elect E.J. Younger, D.A. - complete organization of campaign
1966-1967 Coordinator, Viva Pat Brown Committee L.A. - voter motivation analysis; organized area committees and headquarters; fund-raising; production of effective literature and political machinery.
1967 Director, Public Relations Mex.-Am. Scholarship Fdn.-L.A. - fund-raising; research development brochure
1967-1969 Director's Representative HUD L.A. - under Ignacio Galindo general public relations; HUD intern recruiting, etc.
1969-9/72 Asst. to Director HUD L.A. - under Ray Carrasco overall assistance; public relations; writing and recruiting, etc.
9/72-11/72 Director, Con Nixon Hispanos L.A. - under Alex Armendariz organization of statewide campaign committees of Spanish-speaking Americans; fund-raising and printing of Spanish literature
11/72-7/73 Spanish-speaking coordinator HUD - under Malcolm E. Peabody Division of Equal Opportunity
Marital Status: married Margarita Leonor Varela (b.11/20/24, L.A.) Mexico City, 1/4/65
Daughter: Mrs. Gloria L. Walton (b.1936) Los Altos Hills, Ca.
Naturalized US citizen with no military service.
Memberships:
Pomona Rotary Club 1941-45
Community Service Organization (LA) 1963-68
Mexican-American Political Assn. Southern Regional Director 1963-71
Sister: Mrs. Emma L. Villarrel (La Mesa, Ca.)
Brother-in-law: Juan Manuel Varela (Gabriel, Ca.) b.1932
Scholarship fund set up posthumously.
Scope and Content
Summary: Set is incomplete; there is nothing before 1937, little for 1941 and 1943, and nothing for 1952, 1954 and 1955. There is a partial card file index.
Arrangement
Data organization: Material arranged chronologically.
Container List
- El Espectador, Feb. 1937-Sept. 1938 (Box 1)
  - 1937:
    - Feb. 5. 19, 26
    - Sept. 10, 24
    - Oct. 1, 22, 29
    - Nov. 5, 12, 19, 26
    - Dec. 3, 10, 17
  - 1938:
    - Jan. 21
    - Feb. 18
    - Mar. 18, 25
    - Jun. 3, 10, 17, 24
    - Jul. 1, 15, 22, 29
    - Aug. 5
    - Sept. 2, 9, 23, 30
- Oct. 1938-Sept. 1939 (Box 2)
  - 1938:
    - Oct. 7, 28
    - Nov. 4, 11, 18, 25
    - Dec. 1, 8, 16, 22
  - 1939:
    - Jan. 13, 20, 27
    - Feb. 10, 17, 24
    - Mar. 3, 10, 17, 24, 31
    - Apr. 4, 21, 28
    - May 5, 12, 19, 26
    - Jun. 2, 9, 16, 23
    - Jul. 7, 14, 21
    - Aug. 11, 18, 25
    - Sept. 1
- May-Aug. 1940 (Box 3)
  - May 3, 7, 10, 17, 24
  - Jun. 14, 21, 28
  - Jul. 5, 12, 19, 26
  - Aug. 2, 9, 16, 23, 30
- Sept.-Dec. 1940, 1941, Apr.-Jul. 1942 (Box 4)
  - 1940:
    - Sept. 6, 13, 20, 27
    - Oct. 1, 18, 25
    - Nov. 8, 15, 19, 29
    - Dec. 6, 27
  - 1941:
    - Mar. 4
  - 1942:
    - Apr. 24
    - May 1, 8
    - Jun. 5, 19, 26
    - Jul. 3, 10, 17, 24, 31
- Aug.-Dec. 1942, Jun., Oct.-Dec. 1943 (Box 5)
  - 1942:
    - Aug. 7, 14, 21, 28
    - Sept. 4, 11, 18, 25
    - Oct. 16, 23, 30
    - Nov. 13, 27
    - Dec. 4, 11, 18, 22
  - 1943:
    - Jun. 11
    - Oct. 22
    - Nov. 19
    - Dec. 3, 10, 17, 24, 31
- Jan.-Dec. 1944 (Box 6)
  - Jan. 7
  - Apr. 21, 28
  - May 4, 12, 19, 26
  - Jun. 2, 9, 16
  - Nov. 3, 17
  - Dec. 29
- Jan-Aug 1945 (Box 7)
  - Jan. 5
  - Feb. 2
  - Apr. 6, 13, 20, 27
  - May 18
  - Jun. 1, 6, 15, 22, 29
  - Jul. 6, 13, 27
  - Aug. 3, 10, 17, 24, 31
- Sept.-Dec. 1945 (Box 8)
  - Sept. 7, 14, 21
  - Oct. 5, 12, 26
  - Nov. 2, 9, 16, 23, 30
  - Dec. 7, 14, 28
- Jan.-Jun. 1946 (Box 9)
  - Jan. 18, 25
  - Feb. 1, 8, 15
  - Mar. 1, 8, 15, 22, 29
  - Apr. 5, 12, 19, 26
  - May 3, 10, 17
  - Jun. 7, 14, 28
- Jul.-Sept. 1946 (Box 10)
  - Jul. 12, 19, 26
  - Aug. 2, 9, 16, 23, 30
  - Sept. 6, 13, 20, 27
- Oct.-Dec. 1946 (Box 11)
  - Oct. 4, 11, 18, 25
  - Nov. 1, 8, 15, 22, 29
  - Dec. 6, 13, 20, 31
- Jan.-May 1947 (Box 12)
  - Jan. 10, 24, 31
  - Feb. 7, 14, 21, 28
  - Mar. 7, 14, 21, 28
  - Apr. 11, 18, 25
  - May 2, 9, 16, 23, 30
- Jun.-Sept. 1947 (Box 13)
  - Jun. 6, 13, 20, 27
  - Jul. 4, 11, 18, 25
  - Aug. 1, 8, 15, 22
  - Sept. 5, 12, 19, 26
- Oct.-Dec. 1947 (Box 14)
  - Oct. 3, 10, 17, 24, 31
  - Nov. 7, 14, 21, 28
  - Dec. 5, 12, 19, 26
- Jan.-May 1948 (Box 15)
  - Jan. 9, 16
  - Feb. 6, 13, 20, 27
  - Mar. 5, 12, 19, 26
  - Apr. 2, 9. 16, 23
  - May 7, 15, 21, 28
- Jun.-Aug. 1948 (Box 16)
  - Jun. 4, 11, 18, 25
  - Jul. 2, 16, 23, 30
  - Aug. 6, 13, 20, 27
- Sept.-Dec. 1948 (Box 17)
  - Sept. 3, 12, 17, 24
  - Oct. 1, 8, 15, 22, 29
  - Nov. 5, 12, 19, 24, 26
  - Dec. 3, 10, 17
- Jan.-May 1949 (Box 18)
  - Jan. 14, 21, 28
  - Feb. 4, 11, 18, 25
  - Mar. 4, 11, 18, 25
  - Apr. 1, 8, 15, 29
  - May 6, 13, 20, 27
- Jun.-Sept. 1949 (Box 19)
  - Jun. 3, 10, 17, 24
  - Jul. 7, 15, 22, 29
  - Aug. 12, 19, 26
  - Sept. 2, 9, 16, 23, 30
- Oct.-Dec. 1949 (Box 20)
  - Oct. 7, 14, 21, 28
  - Nov. 4, 11, 18, 25
  - Dec. 2, 9, 16, 23, 30
- Jan.-May 1950 (Box 21)
  - Jan. 6, 13, 20, 27
  - Feb. 3, 10, 17, 24
  - Mar. 3, 7, 10, 17, 24, 31
  - Apr. 14, 21, 28
  - May 5, 12, 19, 26
- Jun.-Sept. 1950 (Box 22)
  - Jun. 2, 9, 16, 23, 30
  - Jul. 7, 14, 21, 28
  - Aug. 4, 11, 18, 25
  - Sept. 1, 8, 15, 22, 29
- Oct.-Dec. 1950 (Box 23)
  - Oct. 6, 13, 20
  - Nov. 1, 3, 10, 17, 24
  - Dec. 1, 8, 15, 22, 29
- Jan.-Jun. 1951 (Box 24)
  - Jan. 5, 12, 19, 26
  - Feb. 2, 9, 16, 28
  - Mar. 2, 9
  - Apr. 6, 13, 20, 27
  - May 4, 11, 18, 25
  - Jun. 1, 8, 15, 22, 29
- Jul.-Dec. 1951 (Box 25)
  - Jul. 6, 13, 21, 27
  - Aug. 3, 10, 17, 24, 31
  - Sept. 7, 14, 21, 28
  - Oct. 5, 12, 19, 26
  - Nov. 2, 9, 16, 20, 30
  - Dec. 7, 14, 20, 28
- Jan-Aug. 1952 (Box 26)
  - Jan. 4, 11, 18, 25
  - Feb. 1, 8, 15, 22, 29
  - Mar. 7, 14, 21, 28
  - Apr. 4, 11, 18, 25
  - May 2, 9, 16, 23, 30
  - Jun. 6, 13, 20
  - Jul. 4, 11, 18, 25, 27
  - Aug. 1, 8
- Feb.-Aug. 1956 (Box 27)
  - Feb. 17
  - Mar. 2, 9, 16, 23, 30
  - Apr. 6, 13, 20, 27
  - May 11, 18, 25
  - Jun. 1, 15, 22, 29
  - Jul. 6, 8, 20, 27
  - Aug. 3, 10, 17, 24, 31
- Sept.-Dec. 1956, Jan.-Mar. 1957 (Box 28)
  - 1956:
    - Sept. 7, 14, 21, 28
    - Oct. 19, 28
    - Nov. 2,9, 16, 30
    - Dec. 7, 14, 21, 28
  - 1957:
    - Jan. 4, 11, 18, 25
    - Feb. 1, 8, 15, 22
    - Mar. 8, 15, 22, 29
- Apr.-Dec. 1957 (Box 29)
  - Apr. 5, 12, 19, 26
  - May 3, 10, 17, 24, 31
  - Jun. 7, 14, 21, 28
  - Jul. 5, 12, 26
  - Aug. 2, 9, 16, 23
  - Nov. 1, 8, 15, 22
  - Dec. 6, 13, 20, 27
- Jan.-Aug. 1958 (Box 30)
  - Jan. 10, 17, 24, 31
  - Feb. 7, 14, 21, 28
  - Mar. 7, 14, 21, 28
  - Apr. 4, 11
  - May 2, 9, 16, 23, 30
  - Jun. 6, 13, 20, 27
  - Jul. 4, 11, 18, 25
  - Aug. 1, 8, 15, 22
- Sept.-Dec. 1958, Jan.-Feb. 1959 (Box 31)
  - 1958:
    - Sept. 5, 12, 19, 26
    - Oct. 3, 10, 17, 24, 31
    - Nov. 7, 14, 21, 28
    - Dec. 5, 12, 19, 26
  - 1959:
    - Jan. 9, 16, 23, 30
    - Feb. 6, 13, 20, 27
- Mar.-Oct. 1959 (Box 32)
  - Mar. 6, 13, 20, 27
  - Apr. 3, 10, 17, 24
  - May 1, 23
  - Jun. 19, 26 (2)
  - Jul. 17, 24, 31
  - Aug. 7, 14, 21, 28
  - Sept. 4, 11, 18
  - Oct. 2, 9, 16, 23, 30
- Nov.-Dec. 1959, Jan.-Sept. 1960 (Box 33)
  - 1959:
    - Nov. 6, 13, 20, 27
    - Dec. 4, 11, 18, 25
  - 1960:
    - Jan. 1, 8, 15, 22, 29
    - Feb. 5, 12, 19
    - Mar. 4, 18, 25
    - Apr. 1, 8, 15, 22, 29
    - May 6, 13, 27
    - Jun. 10, 17
    - Aug. 15, 26
    - Sept. 2
- card file: partial index to El Espectador (Box Box 34:)